<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
    <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on cs2102: Discrete Math</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</webMaster>
    <atom:link href="https://uvacs2102.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/hw0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/hw0/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;homework-0&#34;&gt;Homework 0&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;{{ url_for(&#39;static&#39;, filename=&#39;docs/hw0.pdf&#39;) }}&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;turnin&#34;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable:&lt;/strong&gt; Submit your responses as a single PDF file on the
  collab site before &lt;strong&gt;5:59pm&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;Friday, 26 August&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaboration-policy-read-carefully&#34;&gt;Collaboration Policy - Read Carefully&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this assignment, you may work on your own or with one other student
in the class.  If you work with a partner, you and your partner must
have been born in different counties (if you were both born in the
United States), or in different countries (if one of you was born
outside the United States).  If you work with a partner, you should
submit one assignment that represents your collective best work.
Everyone should understand everything you turn in for the assignment
well enough to be able to produce it completely on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may discuss the assignment with anyone you want and get help from
others, so long as it is help in the spirit of learning how to do things
yourself not getting answers you don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;course pledge&lt;/a&gt; you read and signed at
the beginning of the semester.  For this assignment, you may consult any
outside resources, including books, papers, web sites and people, you
wish &lt;i&gt;except&lt;/i&gt; for materials from previous cs1120 courses.  You may
consult an outside person (e.g., another friend who is a CS major but is
not in this class) who is not a member of the course staff, but that
person cannot type anything in for you and all work must remain your own
and outside sources should never give you specific answers to problem
set questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use resources other than the class materials, lectures and course
staff, you should document this in your turn-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;b&gt;strongly encouraged&lt;/b&gt; to take advantage of the scheduled
 help hours and office hours for this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**1. ** The introduction for the MCS book states,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;laquo;Proofs also play a growing role in computer science; they are used to
certify that software and hardware will &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; behave correctly,
something that no amount of testing can do.&amp;raquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following statements are implied by that statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) Proofs can certify that software and hardware will always behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Testing can never certify that software and hardware will always behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;copy; Proofs can certify that software and hardware will sometimes behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(d)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;course-pledge&#34;&gt;Course Pledge&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/pledge.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor-expectations&#34;&gt;Honor Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a student at the University of Virginia, you are trusted to be
honorable and expected to behave in ways that merit that trust. We take
advantage of this trust to provide a better learning environment for
everyone. In particular, students in cs2102 are expected to follow these
rules throughout the course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will not lie, cheat or steal.&lt;/strong&gt; If I am unsure whether something
  would be considered lying, cheating or stealing, I will ask before
  doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will carefully read and follow the collaboration policy on each
  assignment.&lt;/strong&gt; I will not abuse resources in ways that would be clearly
  detrimental to my own learning or unfair to other students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-expectations&#34;&gt;Other Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the honor rules, students in cs2102 are also expected to
follow these behaviors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will do what I can to help my fellow classmates learn.&lt;/strong&gt; Except when
specifically instructed not to, this means when other students ask me
for help, I will attempt to provide it. I will listen respectfully to
other&amp;rsquo;s ideas and discuss what I think is good or bad about their
answers. When I work with teammates, I will not give or accept answers
directly, but instead will make sure all of my teammates understand
enough to be able to solve the problem themselves, and insist that
teammates explain things to me until I fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will ask for help.&lt;/strong&gt; I will make a reasonable effort to do things on
  my own first (or with my partners for group assignment), but will ask
  the course staff for help before getting overly frustrated. There are
  many ways to ask for help including the office hours and the course
  slack group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will be open minded and curious.&lt;/strong&gt; I understand that this course may
  do things in ways differently from what I expect, and may sometimes
  buck conventions that have been followed in other courses I have
  taken.  I will ask questions when things make me uncomfortable, but
  also accept that being surprised, facing uncertainty and adversity,
  and being challenged unreasonably are often beneficial for learning
  new ways of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I grant the course staff permission to reproduce excerpts from my
submissions for teaching purposes.&lt;/strong&gt; My work will be attributed when it
is shown in a postive way, but may be used anonymously if it is used to
illustrate common pitfalls or other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I will provide useful feedback.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize that this will be
  attempting many new things, and that it is important that I let the
  course staff know what they need to improve the course. I will provide
  feedback either anonymously or by contacting the course staff
  directly.  &lt;strong&gt;I will fill out all requested surveys honestly and
  thoroughly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign:       _______________________________________   &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Date: _____________&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Print name:  ____________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;class-1&#34;&gt;Class 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlighted&#34;&gt;
All course materials are still under development, and subject to change until the first class.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;strong&gt;Thursday&amp;rsquo;s class&lt;/strong&gt;: (visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io&#34;&gt;https://uvacs2102.github.io&lt;/a&gt; for the web version of these notes with links)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs2102.slack.com&#34;&gt;cs2102 slack group&lt;/a&gt; and set up
your profile with a pronouncable name (not your UVA email id) (setting
up your profile photo is encouraged, but not required).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/syllabus&#34;&gt;Course Syllabus&lt;/a&gt; and post any questions or
comments you have on it on the course &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs2102.slack.com&#34;&gt;slack group
(#general)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Chapter 1: What is a Proof?&lt;/em&gt; from the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/mcs.pdf&#34;&gt;MCS Book&lt;/a&gt;.  The book is
freely available on-line under a Creative Commons License.  Students
are strongly encrouaged to print out the readings to read them more
effectively on paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;strong&gt;Friday, 6:29pm&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read, print, and sign the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;Course Pledge&lt;/a&gt;.  You should print
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/pledge.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt; for signing, and submit a scan of
your signed pledge using Collab.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read Jeremy Kun&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jeremyjkun/habits-of-highly-mathematical-people-b719df12d15e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Habits of highly mathematical people&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Submit a [Course Registration Survey] form (which includes some
questions based on Kun&amp;rsquo;s essay).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes-and-questions-pdf-version-only-docs-class1-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;docs/class1.pdf&#34;&gt;Notes and Questions (PDF version only)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;latex&#34;&gt;

Why is most of the math used in computer science _discrete_?

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is most of the math you have used in school previously &lt;em&gt;continuous&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the differences between how scientists, philosophers, and
mathematicians establish &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt; is a statement that is either ________ or _________.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;predicate&lt;/em&gt; is a proposition whose truth may depend on the value of
variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;theorem&lt;/em&gt; is a ____________ that has been proven true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proposition that is believed to be true, but unproven, is called a
_____________.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;axiom&lt;/em&gt; is a proposition that is &lt;em&gt;accepted to be true&lt;/em&gt;.  Axioms are
not proven; they are &lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt; to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; A &lt;em&gt;mathematical proof&lt;/em&gt; of a proposition is a chain of
  &lt;em&gt;logical deductions&lt;/em&gt; starting from a set of accepted &lt;em&gt;axioms&lt;/em&gt; that
  leads to the proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rules-of-inference&#34;&gt;Rules of Inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possible steps that can be used in a proof are logical deductions
based on inference rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inference rules are written as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;table align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;antecedents&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;conclusion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modus Ponens&lt;/em&gt;: It proves &lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt; if you can prove &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; and prove that &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; implies &lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\infer{Q}{P, P \textrm{ implies } Q}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inference rule is &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; if it works for all values of its variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\infer{Q}{P, P \textrm{ implies } Q}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes a proof &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;?
&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;{{ url_for(&#39;static&#39;, filename=&#39;docs/syllabus.pdf&#39;) }}&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cs2102-discrete-mathematics-section-1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cs2102: Discrete Mathematics&lt;/strong&gt; (Section 1)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;university-of-virginia-fall-2016&#34;&gt;University of Virginia, Fall 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 2:00-3:15pm in Chemistry 402.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Objective.&lt;/strong&gt; The goal of this course is to students to
  understand, explain, and apply the foundational mathematical concepts
  at the core of computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skills students learn in this course are essential for later courses
  (especially cs3102 and cs4102, but also in other courses), where they
  will be used to reason about and develop algorithms, prove properties
  about programs, and understand the limits of different models of
  computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected Background:&lt;/strong&gt; The official prerequisite for this course is
  earning credit for CS 1110, 1111, 1112 or 1120 with a grade of C- or
  higher.  If you have not satisfied the official prerequisite, you need
  permission from the instructor to enroll in the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The particular background we assume is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language:&lt;/em&gt; reasonable proficiency in reading and writing English&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Math:&lt;/em&gt; understanding of whole numbers and addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division and exponentiation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Programming:&lt;/em&gt; ability to understand and write simple programs
in some programming language.  In some of the assignments in the
class, students will be expected to read and write short programs in
Python (so students who have not had previous experience with Python
will need to learn a small subset of Python on their own).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computing:&lt;/em&gt; high-level understanding of how computers work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials:&lt;/strong&gt; The primary textbook is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Lehman, F. Thomson Leighton, and Albert R. Meyer. &lt;a href=&#34;../docs/mcs.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mathematics for
Computer Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. (2016/6/16 version).  This book is
freely available on-line, and generously released under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&#34;&gt;Create
Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course will cover most of the first two parts of this book (Chapters
1-13), with some selected materials from later chapters.  In addition to
that textbook, we will have selected readings from other sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;staff&#34;&gt;Staff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teacher:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans&#34;&gt;David Evans&lt;/a&gt; (evans@virginia.edu). My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans/office&#34;&gt;office&lt;/a&gt; is Rice 507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assistant Teachers:&lt;/strong&gt; Adam Guo (BSCS 2018), Adam Rosenberg (MCS 2017), Anindya Prodhan (PhD Student), Brooke Dickie (Systems Engineering 2018), Christopher Long (BACS 2018), Harrison Nam (BSCS 2018), Hussain Humadi (CPE 2018), Jin Han (BSCS 2018), Luke Botti (BACS/Math 2017), Riya Simon (CPE 2019), Saikat Chakraborty (PhD Student), Sarah Barkley (BACS/Math 2018), Sihang Liu (PhD Student), Subhan Poudel (BSCS 2019), Yong Jae Kwon (BACS 2017)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Office Hours:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The course staff is here to help you.&lt;/em&gt; Please don’t
wait until too late to take advantage of the available help or ask for
help. For nearly everyone, this course will involve learning new ways of
thinking that are dramatically different from those to which you are
accustomed.  It is natural to miss things, and then become lost since
new ideas build on previous ones.  Come to office hours early to get
help before you find yourself frustrated and confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office hours schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;officehours.md&#34;&gt;posted on-line&lt;/a&gt;, and will
be kept updated throughout the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;communications&#34;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Website:&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://uvacs2102.github.io/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  All
  course materials will be posted on the course website.  This page is
  updated often and students are expected to visit it regularly. All
  lectures, notes and assignments for the course will be posted on the
  web site.  We encourage students to ask questions about the classes
  and assignments by posting comments on the course blog, and the course
  staff will read and respond to questions there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slack:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs2102.slack.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://cs2102.slack.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  We
  will use a slack group for &amp;laquo;real-time&amp;raquo; communication for quick help
  and discussion (including during lectures).  Unlike the course site,
  which is public and visible to the world, this group will only be
  visible to people in the class.  There are slack apps for web, iOS and
  Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email:&lt;/strong&gt; Feel free to email me (&lt;em&gt;evans@virginia.edu&lt;/em&gt;) with any
  personal questions or issues that should not be posted publicly. For
  general questions or issues that might be relevant for others in the
  class, it is better to post publicly to the course website or slack
  group (both so that others may be able to answer your question, and
  others may be able to see a response that will be useful to them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calendar:&lt;/strong&gt; The course calendar is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=qqvq9kvd197mu6pib4p2uf79q4%40group.calendar.google.com&amp;amp;ctz=America/New_York&#34;&gt;as a Google
  calendar&lt;/a&gt;.
  Students are encouraged to incorporate this into your own calendar.  If you use Google Calendar, just click the &amp;laquo;+&amp;raquo; at the bottom right of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=qqvq9kvd197mu6pib4p2
uf79q4%40group.calendar.google.com&amp;amp;ctz=America/New_York&#34;&gt;calendar page&lt;/a&gt;. If you use another calendar program, you can incorporate this calendar using &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/ical/qqvq9kvd197mu6pib4p2uf79q4%40group.calendar.google.com/public/basic.ics&#34;&gt;ical&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor&#34;&gt;Honor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe strongly in the value of a &lt;em&gt;community of trust&lt;/em&gt;, and expect
all of the students in this class to contribute to strenghtening and
enhancing that community.  The course will be better for everyone if
everyone can assume everyone else is trustworthy. The course staff
starts with the assumption that all students at the university deserve
to be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that expectations are clear to everyone, all students are
required to sign the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;course pledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;topics&#34;&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topics covered in cs2102 focus on developing the mathematical
foundation and skills that are most important for computer science.
Expected topics include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Propositions and Proofs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proof methods (including proof by construction, contradiction, and induction)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logic (Boolean, Logical Formula,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Binary Relations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finite and infinite sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number Theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assignments-and-exams&#34;&gt;Assignments and Exams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A detailed schedule is &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/schedule&#34;&gt;maintained on the course website&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;#calendar&#34;&gt;calendar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key dates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most Fridays (6:29pm): There will be a homework assignment due on
Fridays, except for weeks when there are exams (and Thanksgiving
week).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thursday, 6 October: Exam 1 (in class)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thursday, 10 November: Exam 2 (in class)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saturday, 10 December: Final Exam (9am-noon, scheduled by the registrar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grading&#34;&gt;Grading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grading will be based on your performance on the exams and homework
assignments, with additional adjustments made based on exceptional
contributions to the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grades will be calculated with several different weightings, where your
grade is based primarily on whichever weighting results in the highest
score.  The range of possible weightings is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homeworks: 15-40%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exam 1: 10-25%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exam 2: 15-30%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final Exam: 20-50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class Contribution: 0-25%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend your energy focusing on what you are learning, instead of worrying
about your grade.  Although the material we cover is challenging, and
the pace may seem overwhelming at times, I am confident that all
students who put effort into this class and take good advantage of
available help will do well.  Students who do especially outstanding
work in the course will be offered positions in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jeffersonswheel.org&#34;&gt;my research
group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/main/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>evans@virginia.edu (David Evans)</author>
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/main/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the front page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>