<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cs2102</title>
    <link>//uvacs2102.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on cs2102</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="//uvacs2102.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//uvacs2102.github.io/pages/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//uvacs2102.github.io/pages/syllabus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;syllabus:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;{{ url_for(&#39;static&#39;, filename=&#39;docs/syllabus.pdf&#39;) }}&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cs2102: Discrete Mathematics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mathematics for Computer Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
University of Virginia, Fall 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetings:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 2:00-3:15pm in Chemistry 402.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Objective.&lt;/strong&gt; The goal of this course is to students to
  understand, explain, and apply the foundational mathematical concepts
  at the core of computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skills students learn in this course are essential for later courses
  (especially cs3102 and cs4102, but also in other courses), where they
  will be used to reason about and develop algorithms, prove properties
  about programs, and understand the limits of different models of
  computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected Background:&lt;/strong&gt; The official prerequisite for this course is
  earning credit for CS 1110, 1111, 1112 or 1120 with a grade of C- or
  higher.  If you have not satisfied the official prerequisite, you need
  permission from the instructor to enroll in the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The particular background we assume is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language:&lt;/em&gt; reasonable proficiency in reading and writing English&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Math:&lt;/em&gt; understanding of whole numbers and addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division and exponentiation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Programming:&lt;/em&gt; ability to understand and write simple programs
in some programming language.  In some of the assignments in the
class, students will be expected to read and write short programs in
Python (so students who have not had previous experience with Python
will need to learn a small subset of Python on their own).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computing:&lt;/em&gt; high-level understanding of how computers work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials:&lt;/strong&gt; The primary textbook is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Lehman, F. Thomson Leighton, and Albert R. Meyer. &lt;a href=&#34;../docs/mcs.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mathematics for
Computer Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. (2016/6/16 version).  This book is
freely available on-line, and generously released under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&#34;&gt;Create
Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that textbook, we will have selected readings from other
sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;staff:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Staff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teacher:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans&#34;&gt;David Evans&lt;/a&gt; (evans@virginia.edu). My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/evans/office&#34;&gt;office&lt;/a&gt; is Rice 507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assistant Teachers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Office Hours:&lt;/strong&gt; The course staff is here to help you. Please don’t
wait until too late to take advantage of the available help or ask for
help. For nearly everyone, this course will involve learning new ways
of thinking that are dramatically different from those you are
accustomed to.  It is natural to miss things, and then become lost since
new ideas build on previous ones.  A few minutes in office hours can
enable real understanding and save hours of frustration (as well as
provide the teachers with lots of insight about what is going on in the
class); if that isn&amp;rsquo;t a compelling enough reason, my office has a great
view of the Blue Ridge and occasionally has stray candy for office hours
visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current office hours schedule (which may be revised based on your
registration surveys) is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuesdays, 3:30-4:30pm (Dave, Rice 507)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wednesdays, 4:00-5:30pm (Yuchi, Rice 514)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thursdays, 11:00am-noon (Dave, Rice 507)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fridays, after class-3:00pm (Yuchi, starting in classroom; moving to Rice 514)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;communications:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://xplorecs.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;xplorecs.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  All course
  materials will be posted on the course website.  This page is updated
  often and students are expected to visit it regularly (almost every
  day). All lectures, notes and assignments for the course will be
  posted on the web site.  We encourage students to ask questions about
  the classes and assignments by posting comments on the course blog,
  and the course staff will read and respond to questions there.  You
  may also want to subscribe to email notifications for when the site is
  updated (details provided later), but we will generally not send
  class-wide emails except in exceptional circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slack:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs1120.slack.com&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://cs1120.slack.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  We
  will use a slack group for &amp;ldquo;real-time&amp;rdquo; communication for quick help
  and discussion.  Unlike the course site, which is public and visible
  to the world, this group will only be visible to people in the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email:&lt;/strong&gt; Feel free to email me (&lt;em&gt;evans@virginia.edu&lt;/em&gt;) with any
  personal questions or issues that should not be posted publicly. For
  general questions or issues that might be relevant for others in the
  class, it is better to post publicly to the course website or slack
  group (both so that others may be able to answer your question, and
  others may be able to see a response that will be useful to them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calendar:&lt;/strong&gt; The course calendar is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/embed?src=c9irid4if8aju6s17b7nk6ue8g%40group.calendar.google.com&amp;amp;ctz=America/New_York&#34;&gt;as a Google
  calendar&lt;/a&gt;.
  Students are encouraged to incorporate this into your own calendar.  If you use another calendar program, you can incorporate this calendar using &lt;a href=&#34;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/ical/c9irid4if8aju6s17b7nk6ue8g%40group.calendar.google.com/public/basic.ics&#34;&gt;ical&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;honor:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Honor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe strongly in the value of a community of trust, and expect all
of the students in this class to contribute to strenghtening and
enhancing that community.  The course will be better for everyone if
everyone can assume everyone else is trustworthy. The course staff
starts with the assumption that all students at the university deserve
to be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure that expectations are clear to everyone, all students are
required to sign the &lt;a href=&#34;//uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;course pledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;topics:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Topics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer science is the study of information processes.  Computer
scientists study how to describe, predict properties of, and efficiently
implement information processes.  Students in the course will learn to
design and create computer programs, and to understand and reason about
how those programs execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what we know about describing information processes stems from
three simple ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can define things in terms of themselves (recursive definitions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can treat procedures and data as one and the same (universality).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you give something a name, it becomes more useful (abstraction).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although these ideas are simple, they have profound implications that it
takes many years to fully appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main topics of the course include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language.&lt;/strong&gt; Be able to identify the primitives, means of combination,
  and means of abstraction for a language; describe a language using a
  replacement grammar or recursive transition network; determine the set
  of the surface forms in a language described by a replacement grammar
  or recursive transition network; determine what a surface form in a
  language means if you are given evaluation rules for the language;
  determine the value of a expression following the rules of evaluation.
  Understand an interpreter; modify an evaluator to change the meaning
  of a language; explain why the difference between eagar and lazy
  evaluation matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining and Understanding Procedures.&lt;/strong&gt; Be able to define and
  understand procedures including procedures that take procedures as
  parameters, procedures that produces procedures as results.
  Understand recursive definitions and be able to solve problems by
  defining a recursive procedures and reason about the process produced
  by evaluating an application of a recursively defined procedure.  For
  most of the class, we will use the programming language Python, and
  students will be expected to be able to write and analyze Python
  programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data, Mutation, and Objects.&lt;/strong&gt; Understand how complex data can be
constructed from simple structures, and how to define and manipulate
recursive data structures.  Be able to define, use, and understand
procedures that manipulate lists, trees, and dictionaries.  Define and
understand procedures that use mutation; define procedures that create
objects; explain a class hierarchy; define procedures that use
inheritance; explain how a method is selected given class definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyzing Problems and Procedures.&lt;/strong&gt; Describe problems precisely in
  terms of their inputs and outputs; express the amount of work a
  procedure requires using asymptotic operators; describe a problem
  using &lt;em&gt;O&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;Omega;, and &amp;Theta;; estimate the amount of work a
  solution to a problem involves; classify problems into complexity
  classes P and NP; explain convincingly why a problem is in NP; explain
  what it would mean if someone developed a fast (polynomial time)
  procedure for an NP-Complete problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modeling Computation.&lt;/strong&gt; Explain how to model computation; understand a
  finite state machine description and explain what it does; understand
  a Turing Machine description and explain what it does; show that a
  computing model is (or is not) capable of modeling any mechanical
  computation; explain what it means for an axiomatic system to be
  perfect, incomplete or inconsistent; explain the essence of
  G&amp;ouml;del&amp;#8217;s proof; determine if a problem is computable or
  noncomputable and provide a convincing argument why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assignments-exams-and-grading:051025d606153e159a2b11ffecb897d5&#34;&gt;Assignments, Exams, and Grading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the material in this course is tightly coupled and
interdependent: it is not possible to understand later concepts well,
without understanding what came before.  Hence, assignments and grading
will be done using a progressive model more similar to what is done in
kids Tae Kwon Do classes (and other martial arts) than what most
students are accustomed to in academic classes.  This means you need to
satisfactorily complete the &amp;ldquo;White Belt&amp;rdquo; level assignments before you
can move on to the &amp;ldquo;Yellow Belt&amp;rdquo; assignments.  There will be target
deadlines for each level, but if you do not successfully complete a
level by the target deadline, you will be able to re-attempt it
(possibly doing alternate assignments and oral exams) later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exams for completing each belt will vary in format and structure.  Some
will involve submitting assignments on paper or electronically; others
will include quizzes in writing in class or taken at home; and some will
involve oral exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The target levels for the course are (dates updated from original syllabus):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;White&amp;rdquo; (Monday, 25 January): informal understanding of what a
computer is and what programming a computer involves, ability to write
and understand expressions that manipulate numbers and strings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yellow&amp;rdquo; (Friday, 5 February): understanding conditional and looping
statements, being able to defining and use procedures, and ability to
combine procedures to solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Orange&amp;rdquo; (Monday, 15 February): using and reasoning about structured
data including lists, procedures on recursive data structures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Green&amp;rdquo; (Wednesday, 24 February): designing and manipulating complex
data and programs that operate on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blue&amp;rdquo; (Monday, 21 March): analyzing the cost of executions, basic understanding of
how computing machines work, being able to solve problems without
guidance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Purple/Brown&amp;rdquo; (Monday, 4 April): ability to organize procedures and
state into classes and develop programs using multiple modules and
inheritance, understanding of type systems and their tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Red&amp;rdquo; (Friday, 18 April): understanding of computability and ability to
construct and reason about reduction proofs, interpreters, language
semantics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Black&amp;rdquo; (Monday, 2 May): deep knowledge of major concepts in computer
science; understanding of intractability and its significance; ability
to design and build a complex, interactive application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your final grade in the course will be based on the highest level you
are able to satisfactorily complete.  For students who demonstrate
commendable effort throughout the semester, achieving the Red Belt level
earns an A in the course and Blue Belt earns a B.  The +/- modifiers
reflect quality of work, contributions to the class, and other aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend your energy focusing on what you are learning, instead of worrying
about your grade.  Although the material we cover is challenging, and
the pace may seem overwhelming at times, historically all students who
put effort into this class have done fine.  Although success requires
hard work, all students are expected to get an A in the course.
Students who do especially outstanding work in the course will be
offered paying summer positions in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jeffersonswheel.org&#34;&gt;my research
group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
      <link>//uvacs2102.github.io/main/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//uvacs2102.github.io/main/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//uvacs2102.github.io/images/dm-logo.png&#34; align=&#34;center&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section id=&#34;main&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
   &lt;h1 id=&#34;title&#34;&gt;{{ .Title }}&lt;/h1&gt;
        &lt;ul id=&#34;list&#34;&gt;
            {{ range .Data.Pages }}
                {{ .Render &#34;li&#34;}}
            {{ end }}
        &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>