<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hws on cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
    <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hws on cs2102: Discrete Math</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/hw0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/hw/hw0/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;homework-0&#34;&gt;Homework 0&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;printing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;{{ url_for(&#39;static&#39;, filename=&#39;docs/hw0.pdf&#39;) }}&#34;&gt;PDF for Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;turnin&#34;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable:&lt;/strong&gt; Submit your responses as a single PDF file on the
  collab site before &lt;strong&gt;5:59pm&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;Friday, 26 August&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaboration-policy-read-carefully&#34;&gt;Collaboration Policy - Read Carefully&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this assignment, you may work on your own or with one other student
in the class.  If you work with a partner, you and your partner must
have been born in different counties (if you were both born in the
United States), or in different countries (if one of you was born
outside the United States).  If you work with a partner, you should
submit one assignment that represents your collective best work.
Everyone should understand everything you turn in for the assignment
well enough to be able to produce it completely on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may discuss the assignment with anyone you want and get help from
others, so long as it is help in the spirit of learning how to do things
yourself not getting answers you don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;course pledge&lt;/a&gt; you read and signed at
the beginning of the semester.  For this assignment, you may consult any
outside resources, including books, papers, web sites and people, you
wish &lt;i&gt;except&lt;/i&gt; for materials from previous cs1120 courses.  You may
consult an outside person (e.g., another friend who is a CS major but is
not in this class) who is not a member of the course staff, but that
person cannot type anything in for you and all work must remain your own
and outside sources should never give you specific answers to problem
set questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use resources other than the class materials, lectures and course
staff, you should document this in your turn-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;b&gt;strongly encouraged&lt;/b&gt; to take advantage of the scheduled
 help hours and office hours for this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**1. ** The introduction for the MCS book states,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;laquo;Proofs also play a growing role in computer science; they are used to
certify that software and hardware will &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; behave correctly,
something that no amount of testing can do.&amp;raquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following statements are implied by that statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) Proofs can certify that software and hardware will always behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(b) Testing can never certify that software and hardware will always behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;copy; Proofs can certify that software and hardware will sometimes behave correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(d)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>