<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on cs2102: Discrete Math</title>
    <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on cs2102: Discrete Math</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://uvacs2102.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Office Hours Posted</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/ohours/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/ohours/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/officehours&#34;&gt;Office Hours Schedule&lt;/a&gt; is now posted on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/6KlwNO&#34;&gt;Course
Calendar&lt;/a&gt;.  Office hours start this week Monday
(August 29).  Except for Dave&amp;rsquo;s, all office hours are in Rice 436.
Dave&amp;rsquo;s office hours are in his office, Rice 507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mondays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
9:30-10:30am Dave (Rice 507)&lt;br /&gt;
10:30-1pm Yong Jae, Adam R., Brooke&lt;br /&gt;
4-6:30pm Adam G., Sarah&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesdays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
noon-1:30pm Riya&lt;br /&gt;
3:30-5pm Luke&lt;br /&gt;
7:30-9:30pm Subhan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesdays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
10am-1pm Yong Jae, Brooke, Harrison&lt;br /&gt;
1-2pm Dave (Rice 507)&lt;br /&gt;
2:30-5pm Adam G., Gloria&lt;br /&gt;
6:30-9:30pm Sarah, Han Jin, Subhan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursdays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
10am-1:30pm Harrison, Luke, Han&lt;br /&gt;
3:30-10pm Gloria, Riya, Adam R., Christopher, Subhan, Yaser&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fridays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
9-11:30am Sarah, Yong Jae&lt;br /&gt;
1:30-4pm Luke, Yaser&lt;br /&gt;
5-6pm Hussain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sundays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
noon-3:30pm Hussain, Yong Jae&lt;br /&gt;
4-5:30pm Christopher&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey Questions</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/surveyquestions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/surveyquestions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are my (in progress) responses to selected questions submitted in
the registration surveys.  I&amp;rsquo;ll add more responses here as I go through
the rest of your questions.  If you have other questions after reading
this, feel free to ask them on slack (if you want it to be anonymous,
send it as a direct message and I&amp;rsquo;ll answer it here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
I really hope that you (I&amp;rsquo;m assuming I&amp;rsquo;m talking to the Prof. Evans)
   regularly take a step back from the math we are doing and make an
   effort to explain how the things we are doing relate back to
   computing. In my opinion, this is what will really make the class
   interesting.&lt;br /&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
Yes, I&amp;rsquo;ll definitely try and do this as much as I can.  Some of the
things we cover in this class have direct and immediate relevance to
computing, and I&amp;rsquo;ll aim to point out in classes.  For deeper
understanding of the connections, especially when they are a bit less
direct as is the case for many topics, I think it is probably necessary
to do longer assignments that connect the abstract math concepts to
computing.  I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about doing this some later in the course, but
also want to keep the assignments a reasonable length.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
How does the in class participation work? As in: how do you keep track of who participates?
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;m looking for &amp;laquo;class contribution&amp;raquo;, not just &amp;laquo;participation&amp;raquo;.  Class
contribution means you have done things to make the class better for
your classmates (as well as for me!).  This could be by answering or
asking questions in class, as well as on slack. It could also be by
bringing up interesting ideas or sharing relevant materials or news
items.  I&amp;rsquo;m not keeping track of &amp;laquo;points&amp;raquo; for whenever someone does
something, and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want people to be contributing with &amp;laquo;getting a
point&amp;raquo; as the main motivation.  You should be contributing because you
want to get more out of the class yourself, and because you want to do
things to make the class experience better for everyone.  Even for a
largish class like this, over the course of the semester it is usually
clear which students have made the biggest contributions to the class,
and it will impact their grades favorably.  If you don&amp;rsquo;t stand out as a
class contributor, it won&amp;rsquo;t count against you (the common weighting for
class contribution in the final grade is 0%), but people who contribute
enough to stand out will be rewarded.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
Are there any good external resources/references that would aid me in this course?
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
Yes, there are lots of resources that could be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most useful will be the MIT OpenCourseWare sites for the &amp;laquo;6.042:
Mathematics for Computer Science&amp;raquo; course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-042j-mathematics-for-computer-science-fall-2010/index.htm&#34;&gt;Fall 2010 (Tom Leighton and Marten van Dijk)&lt;/a&gt; (this includes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLB7540DEDD482705B&#34;&gt;lecture videos&lt;/a&gt;, mostly by Tom Leighton, which cover many of the topics in the course)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-042j-mathematics-for-computer-science-spring-2010/&#34;&gt;Spring 2010 (Albert Meyer)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://courses.csail.mit.edu/6.042/spring16/class-material.shtml&#34;&gt;Spring 2016 (Albert Meyer)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll find lots of examples and problems on these sites.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
When AI does everything for us and there are few jobs will you become a Communist?
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
This is a really good question, and something I&amp;rsquo;ve occasionally talked
about (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rust-class.org/class-23-invent-the-future.html&#34;&gt;Invent the
Future!&lt;/a&gt; from my
OS class).  I don&amp;rsquo;t think communism is the answer, but hope we&amp;rsquo;ll get to
some kind of socialist utopia where everyone can have a high quality of
life (well above just subsistance) based on the abundant value that can
be created with automation, but there are opportunities for highly
creative or hard-working individuals to obtain excessive wealth (and
some privileges that go with this) by creating things that have great
benefit to millions or billions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
How did you get so interested in discrete math? It seems like a difficult subject to get in to.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
Most of my interest in the area stems from interest in cryptography and
its applications.  Cryptography is interesting and fun because its about
making and breaking puzzles; its important because it enables private
and secure transactions on open networks, and it changes power
relationships between individuals, organizations, and governments.
Nearly everything in cryptography today builds on concepts from discrete
mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m teaching this course mostly because I like teaching foundational
courses and especially courses early in the curriculum, both for a first
chance to expose students to exciting new ideas and empowering students
more dramatically than can be done in later courses.  The other reasons
I wanted to teach cs2102 are becuase I&amp;rsquo;ve already taught most of the
courses in our curriculum
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs200-spring2002/&#34;&gt;cs200&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs150-fall2005/&#34;&gt;cs150&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xplorecs.org/&#34;&gt;cs1120&lt;/a&gt;;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/intro-to-computer-science--cs101&#34;&gt;cs101
(Udacity)&lt;/a&gt;;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs205-fall2006/&#34;&gt;cs2220&lt;/a&gt;;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs216/&#34;&gt;cs2150&lt;/a&gt;;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs3102-s10/&#34;&gt;cs3102&lt;/a&gt;; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rust-class.org/&#34;&gt;cs4414&lt;/a&gt;) and like to teach new things since
I learn more by doing that, and this course seemed more likely to be a
good source of ideas for &lt;a href=&#34;http://cvillemathcircle.org/&#34;&gt;Cville Math
Circle&lt;/a&gt; than the other core courses I
haven&amp;rsquo;t taught yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
Enjoyed your discussion of using &amp;laquo;hard math problems&amp;raquo; in todays encryption of for example the Bitcoin. Would love future discussions on the subject as it very much interests me.
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
Thanks!  I will try, but worry sometimes students find trangressions
like this confusing (or get worried about whether or not it is something
they need to know for an exam (which hopefully it will be clear when it
isn&amp;rsquo;t).  If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning more about bitcoin, check out my &lt;a href=&#34;bitcoin-class.org&#34;&gt;CryptoCurrency Cabal&lt;/a&gt; course from last year.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
As I said above, I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in cyber-security. Please do continue to frame lessons in applicable contexts. After all, I&amp;rsquo;d love to inspired toward another summer project.
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
 I&amp;rsquo;d like to know more about data security.
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
   Great!  I will keep trying to do this, but also need to limit how
   much time I spend on things too far outside the main course topics.
   If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the work my research group does in security
   and applied cryptography, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www
.jeffersonswheel.org&#34;&gt;https://www.jeffersonswheel.org&lt;/a&gt;.  I am happy to have excellent students join my research group, and anyone who does well in this class will be well-positioned for a summer position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;question&#34;&gt;
What inspired you to join the field of Computer Science in the first place, and how important do you feel this course is to the overall field?
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&#34;answer&#34;&gt;
I had the good fortune to encounter computers when I was in second
grade. My school had a teletype machine with an acoustic coupler modem
(you would dial a phone to connect to the district&amp;rsquo;s headquaters
computer and stick the phon into the coupler).  There was no display,
but it would print out interactions line-by-line.  The good news was
everything was just a BASIC program.  We started by playing the games,
but you could type &lt;code&gt;LIST&lt;/code&gt; and see all the source code and read it to
learn how to &amp;laquo;cheat&amp;raquo; to win the game, and to start changing the code.
The next year, the school got &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_II&#34;&gt;Apple
II&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s, which were fantastic
machines with color graphics (that could display on a TV or monitor) and
even a disk drive that you could use to store programs!  It was so much fun to be able to play around with BASIC programs to draw on the screen, and eventually figure out how to handle key-presses to make games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in middle school, I sold my first program, which was a
program to keep track of team information for the wrestling coach.
Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t test it with more than 10 teammates, so when he
tried entering the team in it the program crashed when he got to the
11th person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew programming computers was a lot of fun, but didn&amp;rsquo;t know anything
about computer science (or that I wanted to do it for a career), until
taking Gerry Sussman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-001-structure-and-interpretation-of-computer-programs-spring-2005/video-lectures/&#34;&gt;6.001 Structure and Interpretation of Computer
Programs&lt;/a&gt;
course (at MIT in 1989).  That opened me to the power and beauty of
computer science, beyond just writing programs, and I&amp;rsquo;ve only had a few
digressions since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to why cs2102 (and the other theoretical and foundational courses you
take) is important, courses like these are the ones that should empower
you to envision and execute creative computing beyond standard practice.
There are tons of 3-month boot camps that can train most smart people to
become adequate web and mobile developers or data scientist programmers,
and people who complete these programs are able to find good six-figure
jobs.  The best of them will stay active in learning new APIs and tools,
and develop the experience needed to build increasingly complex
projects.  If you want to do that you don&amp;rsquo;t need to do a four-year
degree at an expensive University like UVa &amp;mdash; there are much
easier, faster, and cheaper career paths to being a professional
programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, people without fundamental understanding of the
underlying mathematics and theory of computing (which you should get
from cs2102, cs3102, and cs4102), and deep understanding of how
computing systems work (which you should get from cs2150, cs3330, and
cs4414), are unlikely to do things that really advance the state of
computing.  Most programmers do things that are unsurprising and
mundane; you should aspire to do things that are surprising and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarkefoundation.org/about-sir-arthur/sir-arthurs-quotations/&#34;&gt;indistinguishable from
magic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I hope cs2102 will be valuable and exciting on its own, its
real importance in the curriculum and your overall computing
development, is to prepare you well for cs3102 and cs4102.  As a whole,
though, the foundational understanding you should get from those courses
should enable you to design, build, and analyze computing systems that
do things people previously thought were not possible (or didn&amp;rsquo;t even
think about at all!)&lt;br /&gt;
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problem Set 1</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/ps1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/ps1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem Set 1&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/ps/ps1&#34;&gt;now posted&lt;/a&gt;, and is due on &lt;strong&gt;Friday, 2 September at 6:29pm&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 2: Proof Methods</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/class2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/class2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;strong&gt;Friday (tomorrow), 6:29pm&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read, print, and sign the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;Course Pledge&lt;/a&gt;.  You should print
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/pledge.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt; for signing, and submit a scan of
your signed pledge using Collab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read Jeremy Kun&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jeremyjkun/habits-of-highly-mathematical-people-b719df12d15e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Habits of Highly Mathematical People&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submit a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSesDMnQXhCP73thN51kTSNNst8GcvQCJCGTepiJ2c3Ym1l-zg/viewform&#34;&gt;Course Registration Survey&lt;/a&gt; (which includes some questions based on Kun&amp;rsquo;s essay).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before Tuesday&amp;rsquo;s class: Read MCS Chapter 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before Thursday&amp;rsquo;s class: Read MCS Chapter 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due Friday at 6:29pm: &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/ps/ps1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem Set 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;notpdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry the proof in class got so messed up!  Although part of my goal for
class today was to illustrated the subjectiveness of human-written and
read proofs, I apologize for making things so confusing and broken.  I&amp;rsquo;d
updated the notes to include the full proof (hopefully correct now!) at
the level of detail intended in class.  Its good to see students are
being skeptical proof-readers and noticing mistakes like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t get to the &amp;laquo;if and only if&amp;raquo; proof in the notes in class today,
but you are encouraged to try this on your own.  We&amp;rsquo;ll look at this the
Well Ordering Principle (Chapter 2) in Tuesday&amp;rsquo;s class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlightr&#34;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Challenge Problem Opportunity.&lt;/strong&gt; I wasn&amp;rsquo;t very satisfied with my proof
  of the &amp;laquo;Odd-Even Lemma&amp;raquo; in class.  I hope a student will come up with
  a better proof.  A proof that passes the &amp;laquo;skeptical reader&amp;raquo; test and
  would convince someone with no prior knowledge of odd and even numbers
  is worth up to 10 bonus points.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlightm&#34;&gt;
   &lt;a href=&#34;docs/class2.pdf&#34;&gt;See PDF Version for &lt;b&gt;Notes and Questions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
   &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;d7b6ff339db149ba8996cfcc6d84d44d&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.77777777777778&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;links&#34;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Ariely, &lt;a href=&#34;http://more-minerals.blogspot.com/2016/02/dan-ariely-honor-codes.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Honor Codes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coq Proof Assistant tool I mentioned in class today is available
from &lt;a href=&#34;https://coq.inria.fr/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;https://coq.inria.fr/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  (You are not
expected to use this for cs2102, or generate proofs at this level of
rigor or details, but are certainly welcome to if you want!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2009/06/us_airways200906&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anatomy of a
Miracle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
Vanity Fair, June 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trnicely.net/pentbug/pentbug.html&#34;&gt;Intel&amp;rsquo;s FDIV bug&lt;/a&gt; (there&amp;rsquo;s even a web page for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.columbia.edu/~sss31/rainbow/pentium.jokes.html&#34;&gt;jokes about Intel&amp;rsquo;s FDIV bug&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--endpdf--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;latex&#34;&gt;

# Notes and Questions

An integer, $z$, is **even** if there exists an integer $k$ such that $z = 2k$.    

Is this a _definition_, _axiom_, or _proposition_?

#

An integer, $z$, is **odd** if there exists an integer $k$ such that $z
= 2k + 1$.  (Note that there is no connection between the variables used
here, and to define even above.)

To prove an implication, $P \implies Q$: 1. assume $P$.  2. Show chain of logical deductions that leads to $Q$.

**Odd-Even Lemma:** If an integer is not even, it is odd.  Note: A
  _lemma_ is just a name for a theorem, typically used for proving
  another theorem.

&lt;div class=&#34;biggap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How should one decide what can be accepted as an axiom, and what must be proven?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the purpose of a &lt;em&gt;proof&lt;/em&gt;?  (in cs2102? in software development? in algorithm design?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;proof-from-class&#34;&gt;Proof from Class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposition: If the product of $x$ and $y$ is even, at least one of $x$ or $y$ must be even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to prove the implication, $P \implies Q$, where:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$P$ is &amp;laquo;the product of $x$ and $y$ is even&amp;raquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$Q$ is &amp;laquo;at least one of $x$ and $y$ must be even&amp;raquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will prove the contrapositive.  The inference rule,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
\infer{P \implies Q}{NOT(Q) \implies NOT(P)}
$$
will be the last step in our proof.  To be able to use this rule, we need to make the antecedent true.  So, our goal is to prove $NOT(Q) \implies NOT(P)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove an implication, we assume the left side and short the right
side.  So, our proof begins:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We prove the contrapositive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume NOT(at least one of $x$ and $y$ must be even).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the meaning of negation, this means both $x$ and $y$ are not even.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the &amp;laquo;Odd-Even Lemma&amp;raquo;, both $x$ and $y$ are odd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the definition of &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt;, there exist integers $k$ and $m$ such that $x = 2k + 1$ and $y = 2m + 1$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substituting, $xy = (2k + 1)(2m + 1) = 4mk + 2m + 2k + 1 = 2(2mk + m + k) + 1$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the closure of addition and multiplication over the integers, there is some integer $r = 2mk + m + k$, so $xy = 2r + 1$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the definition of &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt;, $xy$ is odd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the (not proven) &amp;laquo;Even-Odd Lemma&amp;raquo;, this means $xy$ is not even.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So, we have shown NOT(the product of $x$ and $y$ is even).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since we concluded this starting from the assumption (step 2), this proves the implication: NOT(at least one of $x$ and $y$ must be even) $\implies$ NOT(the product of $x$ and $y$ is even).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the contrapositive inference rule, we can conclude:
the product of $x$ and $y$ is even $\implies$ at least one of $x$ and $y$ must be even. \QEDA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\dbox{
{\bf Challenge Problem Opportunity.} I wasn&amp;rsquo;t very satisfied with my proof
  of the &amp;laquo;Odd-Even Lemma&amp;raquo; in class.  I hope a student will come up with
  a better proof.  A proof that passes the &amp;laquo;skeptical reader&amp;raquo; test and
  would convince someone with no prior knowledge of odd and even numbers
  is worth up to 10 bonus points.
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--page--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;proving-if-and-only-if&#34;&gt;Proving &amp;laquo;If and Only If&amp;raquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy: To prove $P$ if and only if $Q$:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prove $P \implies Q$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prove $Q \implies P$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Definition.&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;em&gt;standard deviation&lt;/em&gt; of a sequence of values $x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n$ is
$$
\sqrt{\frac{(x_1 - \mu)^2 + (x_2 - \mu)^2 + \ldots + (x_n - \mu)^2}{n}}
$$
where $\mu$ is the mean of the values:
$$
\mu ::= \frac{x_1 + x_2 + \ldots + x_n}{n}
$$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1.6.1.&lt;/strong&gt; The standard deviation of a sequence of values, $x_1,
  x_2, \ldots, x_n$ is $0$ &lt;em&gt;if and only if&lt;/em&gt; all of the $x_i$ values are
  equal to the mean of $x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book proves this using a chain of iff implications; prove it using
the two-implications strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In physics, your solution should convince a reasonable person. In math, you have to convince a person who&amp;rsquo;s trying to make trouble.&lt;/em&gt;
Frank Wilczek&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class 1</title>
      <link>https://uvacs2102.github.io/class1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uvacs2102.github.io/class1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;strong&gt;Thursday&amp;rsquo;s class&lt;/strong&gt;: (visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io&#34;&gt;https://uvacs2102.github.io&lt;/a&gt; for the web version of these notes with links)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://csmath.slack.com&#34;&gt;cs2102 slack group&lt;/a&gt; and set up
your profile with a pronouncable name (not your UVA email id) (setting
up your profile photo is encouraged, but not required).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/syllabus&#34;&gt;Course Syllabus&lt;/a&gt; and post any questions or
comments you have on it on the course &lt;a href=&#34;https://csmath.slack.com&#34;&gt;slack group
(#general)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Chapter 1: What is a Proof?&lt;/em&gt; from the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/mcs.pdf&#34;&gt;MCS Book&lt;/a&gt;.  The book is
freely available on-line under a Creative Commons License.  Students
are strongly encrouaged to print out the readings to read them more
effectively on paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before &lt;strong&gt;Friday, 6:29pm&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read, print, and sign the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/pledge&#34;&gt;Course Pledge&lt;/a&gt;.  You should print
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uvacs2102.github.io/docs/pledge.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt; for signing, and submit a scan of
your signed pledge using Collab.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read Jeremy Kun&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@jeremyjkun/habits-of-highly-mathematical-people-b719df12d15e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Habits of Highly Mathematical People&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Submit a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSesDMnQXhCP73thN51kTSNNst8GcvQCJCGTepiJ2c3Ym1l-zg/viewform&#34;&gt;Course Registration Survey&lt;/a&gt; (which includes some questions based on Kun&amp;rsquo;s essay).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;notpdf&#34;&gt;

    &lt;div class=&#34;highlightm&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;docs/class1.pdf&#34;&gt;See PDF Version for &lt;b&gt;Notes and Questions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;script async class=&#34;speakerdeck-embed&#34; data-id=&#34;460cc29c74a04fe3971ce197961981f9&#34; data-ratio=&#34;1.77777777777778&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--endpdf--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;latex&#34;&gt;

### Notes and Questions

Why is most of the math used in computer science _discrete_?

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is most of the math you have used in school previously &lt;em&gt;continuous&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the differences between how scientists, lawyers, and
mathematicians establish ``&lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;gap&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt; is a statement that is either ________ or _________.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;predicate&lt;/em&gt; is a proposition whose truth may depend on the value of
variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;proof&#34;&gt;Proof&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;theorem&lt;/em&gt; is a ____________ that has been proven true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;axiom&lt;/em&gt; is a proposition that is &lt;em&gt;accepted to be true&lt;/em&gt;.  Axioms are
not proven; they are &lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt; to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition.&lt;/strong&gt; A &lt;em&gt;mathematical proof&lt;/em&gt; of a proposition is a chain of
  &lt;em&gt;logical deductions&lt;/em&gt; starting from a set of accepted &lt;em&gt;axioms&lt;/em&gt; that
  leads to the proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rules-of-inference&#34;&gt;Rules of Inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possible steps that can be used in a proof are logical deductions
based on inference rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inference rules are written as:
$$
\infer{\textrm{\emph{conclusion}}}{\textrm{\emph{antecedents}}}
$$
This means if everything on top of the rule is established to be true,
then you can conclude what is on the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modus Ponens&lt;/em&gt;: To prove &lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;, (1) prove &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; and (2) prove that &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; implies &lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;.  ($P \implies Q$ is a notation for $P$ implies $Q$).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
\infer{Q}{P,\quad P \implies Q}
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inference rule is &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; if can never lead to a &lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt; conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of these inference rules are sound?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
\infer{Q}{P}
\qquad
\infer{false}{P, P \implies Q}
\qquad
\infer{true}{P, NOT(P)}
\qquad
\infer{P \implies NOT(P)}{P, NOT(P)}
\qquad
\infer{NOT(Q) \implies P}{NOT(P) \implies Q}
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contrapositive:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
\infer{NOT(Q) \implies NOT(P)}{P \implies Q}
\qquad
\infer{P \implies Q}{NOT(Q) \implies NOT(P)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem to Prove:&lt;/strong&gt; If the product of $x$ and $y$ is even, at least one of $x$ or $y$ must be even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>